What are you doing there ?
My letter to the Maréchal. It's for Monday.
Do you want me to read it to you ?
If you want.
Monsieur le Maréchal, since the Summer,
German soldiers are among us...
... and our soldiers are in Germany.
It would be damned simple
if the German soldiers were in Germany,
and our soldiers were at home.
Where did you find that ?
I don't know. Isn't it any good ?
Yes, yes.
But you must apply yourself,
it's almost unreadable.
Your a's look o's.
I've already told you a hundred times.
And you can't write "damned simple" .
Just say... "it would be good."
...or something like that.
But it will be full of rubbings out !
Well then, recopy it.
But I'll have less pages in my notebook.
Well use a sheet of paper.
It's not too early, eh!
The Germans have strengthened their controls
for November 11th. I ran into a checkpoint.
They searched the van thoroughly.
Fortunate that we haven't yet slipped in the flyers.
Good day to you.
Hello Madame, do you want me to
read you my letter to the Maréchal ?
We don't have time Gustave.
Copy your letter and apply yourself.
Good. They dropped them off ?
Of course, no question. What do you take me for ?
Suzanne, the plan assumed that nothing in your
schedule would differ from normal.
We need an hour to insert the flyers.
That gets you to the Post Office at 9 o'clock.
It means that people are going
to see you arrive late.
But not necessarily. There won't be
many people near the garage exit.
Even if someone sees me arrive at 9 o'clock
what proof is there I just came from Sayolle ?
I could very well have arrived
at 8 o'clock, and gone out again.
Gone where ?
I don't know.
To a café !
In this cold.
The only café open at that time
is the Station Café...
... the owner is a police informer.
If you say that, you'll sleep in jail.
No.      I arrived from Sayolle at 8 o'clock.
I was late because of the checkpoint.
I dropped the papers on the loading dock and...
...I went to the cemetery
To pray at my father's grave.
I go there regularly at that time.
There's never anyone there.
Why did you drop off the papers
before going to pray ?
It's the rule.
We must drop the papers on the loading dock
as soon as they arrive.
The rule says it's the first item of business.
It could work.
But if someone sees you leave the papers
at 9 o'clock and not 8, it'll show you're lying.
But no-one goes there.
It's a creepy cul-de-sac.
Who is working with you today ?
Madame Morvandieu.
She never arrives before half past nine. Ever.
She comes on foot. She has problems with rheumatism
Hey, may I have some ?
Excuse me, of course.
Thank you.
Listen to me, Gustave.
Today, I'm not taking you to school on the bike.
Right, but why ?
Because of work, Gustave.
I have to take this lady to work.
So you're going on foot.
But I don't like to walk when it's dark.
And it's cold.
No use discussing it, Gustave.
I can't do anything else.
And listen, if you are asked about this lady,
you don't know her. OK ?
COLD SNAP
Suzanne, stop.
The string is too tight.
I can't slide in the flyers.
Shit. This is tighter than usual !
Probably because of the German insert
for November 11th.
Now what ?
See, we can only do about a score of them.
Those on the outside.
We can't take such risks for 20 flyers.
We need to cut the strings.
But how do we re-tie the packets ?
We'll tie new knots.
That'll be noticed...
...if the packets are not exactly as usual,
The Police will ask why you didn't report it.
Do you have string at the sawmill ?
It's not far.
You're afraid !
You're not ?
Yes.
The sawmill night watchman will be gone by now.
Schwartz and the first employees
won't be there before 9 o'clock.
How long to get there ?
A quarter of an hour.
That leaves us 30 minutes to slip in the flyers
10 minutes to go to the sawmill...
20 minutes to re-tie the strings...
10 minutes to get to the Post Office. OK.
It'll still work.
It's up to you.
Can I get you some more coffee ?
No thanks, I'm finished.
It's cold this morning !
I must get over to the Soup Distribution.
Are you coming with me ?
Is it really necessary ?
You're still the Mayor's wife.
... and the prettiest woman in Villeneuve.
Marchetti, don't you think that she's
the prettiest woman in Villeneuve ?
Ah, I can't permit myself Monsieur le Maire.
Even if it's me that's asking ?
Well, you see you're
boring him with your questions.
While one's eating, one doesn't want
to be answering questions.
Really ? Good! I'll get ready.
You'll get used to it eventually.
I think we get used to everything.
That's true.
Docteur, old Camille's neighbour phoned.
He's worried. He hasn't been seen
since the day before yesterday.
Very good. Call the Secours National.
No leave it, I'll go by there.
Old Camille is a bit tiring,
but I like him.
Good day, Lucienne.
Good day, Headmaster.
I asked Feldwebel Wagner to be present
at the reading of letters to the Maréchal.
Good.
The Maréchal said we need to collaborate,
so let's collaborate.
And as the Inspection guy will be here,
it'll make a pretty good impression.
I hope my presence doesn't
disturb you too much, Mademoiselle.
No, no. Not at all.
My brother is a teacher in Saarbrucken.
Herr Feldwebel, you sit there
I'll sit there...
... and Mr Foulquier,
indeed he'll sit wherever he wants.
Is this the Monsieur Foulquier who...
Yes. Yes, yes. I've seen your file.
That affair was really unfortunate.
But in the end, obviously,
they pigeon-holed the thing.
Don't worry.
There you are.
I don't usually come on foot.
So I've arrived early as it was cold
You did well.
Your Papa couldn't bring you ?
Ah, Gustave Larcher !
You've done your letter, I hope ?
Ah yes, Monsieur.
And even my Papa said it was fine.
Well, let's see it.
Excuse me. We have a problem with the
light downstairs. Do you have
the keys to the meter box ?
Certainly.
Can you show us Lucienne ?
You stay here, I'll be back.
You told me the watchman
wasn't here tonight.
It's Marcel !
I don't know why he's come
to mess around at this hour.
It's cold. Warm me up.
He's stealing string ?
I mustn't linger.
When Laurin goes to see the kids...
He always returns early next day
for the milking.
You're...
And with Jeannine ?
Where are you with that ?
Nowhere.
It'll subside.
L'Etat Francaise expresses itself through me...
... assuring you of its sincere solidarity.
These blankets, and this soup which are offered
by the Sous-Préfecture and with the assistance...
...of the Food Agency
and the Secours National.
These blankets, and this soup,
are the warmth of renewal...
...of French renewal that
we must build together.
Under the leadership of the
venerable and glorious victor of Verdun.
Thank you.
I think we can move on to the distribution of soup.
A very good speech, Monsieur le Sous-Préfet.
Hold on there.
The French are really just bellies.
With the cold and the Germans taking everything,
this is quite natural.
They're not taking everything dear Madame.
That's a myth.
It's bizarre, all the same,
not commemorating the 11th of November.
What I mean is I noticed you called him
the victor of Verdun...
... that was very good.
Monsieur le Maire.
Inspecteur Marchetti reports
that old Camille has died.
And he'll wait on you for the death certificate.
Poor old man, I liked him a lot.
It's imperative that we wait for von Ritter.
I'll go there, after all a death certificate
isn't that complicated.
That's not very funny, you know.
But I've already done others, remember.
And it's always less boring
than Servier's speeches.
I'll go with you.
Try to get names of people...
... people to inform of his death.
Monsieur le Maire, Monsieur le Sous-Préfet.
You must prevent any
patriotic demonstrations on November 11th.
Don't worry. When people are satisfied,
they don't think.
Why do you think we've organized this today ?
Very good. And I must also inform you
that we're going to keep guard...
...with two sentries at the War Memorial
in the Grand-Place.
You're afraid the dead will demonstrate ?
You should know that my father
died on the Sambre in 1917...
... and I personally regret
that no commemoration is possible...
... but like my father, I'm a soldier
and I carry out orders.
I thought that after Montoire,
an effort would have been made for the POWs.
That will surely come.
The Maréchal knows what he's doing.
But to guard the War Memorial.
No, that becomes...
Have you seen they've put
three Ls in 'eternellle' ?
I hadn't seen that.
It's annoying.
In any case thank you for coming
before your work starts, Madame Morvandieu.
It's mainly my rheumatism.
I'm glad the distribution has ended so early.
Suddenly I'm early.
On a day like today I don't think we'll have
many people at the Post Office.
I'm getting out here.
We can't risk being seen together.
How's it going to go ?
What's the worst we risk ?
I don't know.
You don't have to do it Suzanne.
No, of course not.
But in the end, yes. In fact right now.
So we need to get going.
Time's against us.
Remember, no contact for three days.
No matter what.
Do I start now, or wait ?
Might as well wait for him.
All these missing children bother me.
We'll tell him it's because of the cold.
Foulquier is a creep, but he's not an idiot.
He's even capable of asking me
to send him a list of all the absentees.
Hey !
You, wake up, eh !
Please, sit down. Sit down
Headmaster.
Inspecteur.
Mademoiselle Borderie.
We're delighted to have you here
for this great occasion.
Ah yes. I have something to
say to them before we start.
Please. Go ahead.
Children, you are the future
of the French nation...
... by writing to the Maréchal
it is to France you are writing.
The real France freed of her bad habits...
...of the lies that did her so much harm...
...and the parasites who got rich on her back.
My dear children, the Maréchal hears you.
One moment. I took the liberty of inviting the
Feldwebel who lives in the school.
I'll go and get him.
Ah yes.
He should have avoided that
on the 11th of November, though.
It will reduce waste.
It must be ready for tomorrow at 3 o'clock.
Go on.
Good day Marcel. Good day Hervé. Hello Marcel.
Good day Monsieur Schwartz.
Is it a German order ?
Oh no, this is for the Parisians.
They're in a hurry.
What's more they don't want pine.
They want oak.
We should have sent them to look elsewhere.
I'll take care of it for now.
Hey, what were you doing here this morning ?
This morning ?
Yes. I arrived early, I saw you.
I forgot my cigarettes.
I've none stored at home.
That's funny because I saw you take some string.
It doesn't bother me that
you were taking string...
... but given the time of day,
it surprised me a bit.
You mustn't have seen it properly.
I took my cigarettes.
You know, with all the restrictions
you should stop smoking in the morning.
Otherwise you won't last the month.
That's easier said than done.
I'll get on with the von Ritter order.
Ah... You scared me.
To tell the truth, you scared me too.
Daniel is busy at the Mairie,
so I'm substituting for him.
This is definitely not work for a woman.
You know, in assisting Daniel with corpses,
I've seen others.
The poor old man must have had a weakness.
He died of cold.
When I found him he was quite stiff.
His window was open. Do you know why ?
He often slept with the window open,
to let his pigeon return.
He's definitely dead.
I found this Interzonal Postcard.
Signed Annette. There's an address in Nice.
Ah, that's good, we can inform her.
Yes.
Will you help me ?
Hold on. Ah, thank you.
What time is it ?
It's for the certificate.
10 am.
Actually, five minutes to, to be exact.
It was very cold yesterday.
You didn't think so ?
Yes.
How was the soup distribution ?
Lukewarm.
I wanted to tell you I'm very happy
to be in your home.
Me too, I'm pleased you're staying with us.
It's the newspaper.
11th of November 1940
OUT WITH THE GERMANS !
True patriots who want to do something.
VIVE LA FRANCE !
Monsieur le Maréchal,
I would like you to bring home
my friend's Papa for Christmas
And I would like chocolates
and sweets for Christmas Day.
Because there no longer are any,
and it's not fair.
That's good.
Show me the letter.
This is good but we can't send it
to the Maréchal.
Why ?
Because today there are more
important things than chocolate.
Do you ever explain to them
a little about what France is...
Germany, Collaboration,
the National Revolution.  No ?
Never ?
Monsieur, we follow the Official Guidelines.
The Academy has sent us nothing.
You must anticipate the Official Guidelines.
Today's problem is not finding chocolate,
it's to reform France...
... after cleaning it up.
Do you understand that ?
Yes.
Good, go back to your place.
Next.
Le Dantec.
The Flyers couldn't have been
inserted in a couple of minutes.
As on every night, the Sayolle depot
was unsupervised from 4 to 6.
Or even later, which implies involvement
of the Post Office head.
Why not at the newspaper ?
Because there was a German
censorship guy there that evening.
He told me everything was normal
and I think we can believe him.
The Germans will crucify us.
Right. Do we have the means
of finding out who did this ?
Yes or no ?
Hang on. We're a long way from
kids whistling in a cinema, here.
Exactly, it's worse. These are people
directly opposed to the Maréchal.
No. Who oppose the Germans.
Since Montoire it's the same thing.
Come on, pull yourself together.
You mentioned the head of the Post Office ?
Suzanne Richard.
38 years old, seven years seniority,
married with two children.
Communist ?
Not that we know.
Her husband was in the SFIO in 1936.
Yes. And now he's a POW in a Stalag.
I still think she's a suspect.
Monsieur le Maire, I'd be happy if this
were investigated by Inspecteur Marchetti.
I am at your disposal.
So proceed.
To mount a such a coup it first
had to be conceived, then organised.
The flyers printed, and several secret meetings.
I think we're dealing with a group.
A Communist group.
'Germans Out !' is not really the Party Line.
Yes. But they're the only ones
to have the organisation.
Which brings me to a delicate point
Monsieur le Maire.
What ?
Your brother was fingered as
a Communist in 1936 ?
In 1936. Only in 36 !
But I've every reason to believe that last January
he formed a Party cell in the Schwartz sawmill.
You're not, however, going to
investigate my brother ?
Listen, Larcher. When it was Bellini,
we went after his son...
Marchetti's right. It's in showing that Order rules
without exception, that we'll carry people with us.
I think we need to start with the Postmistress.
She was seen arriving at 9am
which indicates a large delay.
And if this lead doesn't pan out,
I'll venture to call in your brother.
Just to see.
The youngest, Gustave Larcher.
Is Larcher the Mayor's son ?
His nephew.
It will perhaps be good to select his letter.
Let's wait and see what's in it.
We're listening.
Monsieur le Maréchal.
Since the Summer, German soldiers are with us
and our soldiers are in Germany.
It would, however...
...be even better if the
German soldiers were in Germany,
and our soldiers were here at home....
Good. This is very good.
Really !
Let me see your letter.
Wait!
This is not good at all !
Not good at all.
The German soldiers are very happy to be in France.
Bad propaganda.
Yes, yes. Indeed, it's not good.
This is not good at all.
This is really not a good idea.
So you, I don't know...I don't really know
what's going through your head.
Back to your place, you bad boy.
These Boches !
It was slipped in the paper this morning.
What is this thing ?
You've broken off with the Postmistress ?
Obviously, why ?
Is she involved ?
Well, the cops think she is.
How do you know ?
You ask too many questions, Comrade.
We know, that's all.
She arrived late for work.
She'll be arrested soon, for sure.
Listen, the Comrades are worried about
your past relationship with her.
The Party can't be involved in a provocation.
'Germans Out !'
How can they think the Party is involved.
It doesn't make sense.
Hey, Max, can you move your truck ?
What's this ?
I don't know.
It's a letter from your father.
You don't recognize his handwriting ?
What does he say ?
You know what he says.
He asks me to get rid of Marie and Laurin.
Listen, he's the owner.
And you really think your father
should arrange our affairs ?
Since you won't do anything about it...
You're hurting me.
It's a simple fad. A moment of madness
that she surely regrets as much as me.
I want you to get rid of that slut.
Nobody can force me to do
something I don't want to do.
Do you know that ?
Do you know why you're here, Madame Richard ?
I guess it's over this stupid story of the leaflets.
Why stupid ? These are very good leaflets.
And between us, we'd all like
the Germans to leave.
What time did you arrive at work this morning ?
About 8 o'clock, as every morning.
Shortly before ? Shortly after ?
I'm sorry. I have to be precise.
I seem to have heard the
church bell just after, but...
.. I'm not sure.
So you arrived at 8am and dropped
the papers on the dock. Is that correct ?
Well yes.
And you didn't see anything special ?
No. You know, a bundle of papers,
is a bundle of papers.
That's right.
And you're sure it was really 8 o'clock ?
Yes.
And between 8 and 9, what did you do ?
I went to pray at my father's grave.
An hour of prayer ?
Well you know, plus the time to return...
... smoke a little cigarette...
This is great. So we'll certainly
find the butt, then.
In fact, no. I didn't actually smoke today,
now that I recall...
Since the cold wave I've had a sore throat.
And besides, I shared my last cigarette
with Madame Morvandieu yesterday.
Who saw you arrive at 9 o'clock.
Pardon ?
Yes. Because Madame Morvandieu
arrived early this morning.
She distributed the soup at the Mairie, and...
...she saw you unload papers at 9 o'clock.
... not 8 o'clock.
We're sure of the time because it was
Monsieur le Maire himself who saw her leave.
Yes. It was her then.
I believe I saw her.
So you acknowledge that you dropped off
the papers at 9 o'clock ?
Yes.
And you acknowledge that you
participated in this little action ?
Not at all, I had nothing to do with it.
Why did you lie about your arrival time, then ?
Because of the Regulations.
The Regulations require us to drop off
the papers before any other business.
So today, as I knew no-one would arrive
before half past nine, I said...
...I'll go and pray first, and drop them at 9.
You won't talk to the Regional Office ?
Because with a story like that
I risk a penalty.
So ?
She's involved. I've put her in a cell.
She confessed ?
No. Remarkably she agreed with
the testimony of Madame Morvandieu.
So far, I have nothing.
But behind the facade, I sense fear.
Yes, I feel her fear.
I didn't understand what got into Fritz,
It was a very good letter.
I'm on the verge of asking for an
explanation from the Kommandantur.
That he didn't like the letter. Fine !
But to burn it !
The Germans are unpredictable.
That may be why they've won the war.
I'll go and watch the children's break.
You're right.
See you soon, Lucienne.
Thank you.
I don't know her political views.
You think we discuss politics at the moment ?
When she unloaded the papers,
did you see anyone with her ?
No !
Do you know if she has the habit
of praying in the graveyard ?
Yes. At her father's grave.
Almost every morning.
She did nothing strange in recent weeks ?
I don't know. What does that mean. Strange ?
Something unusual.
Madame Morvandieu, if you hide something from us,
whatever it is.
You'll be complicit in
something very serious.
Do you understand that ?
I don't want to harm her reputation.
She's such a good woman...
...and with her husband in a Stalag...
...but there were days, during the lunch break,
when I saw her talking with a man.
They seemed to know each other well.
Oh, they did nothing wrong...
... but they seemed to know each other.
Who was it ?
That's what surprised me, it was
the Mayor's brother, Marcel Larcher.
The guy at the sawmill.
I had no idea that she knew him.
I don't want them to be persecuted.
Laurin is a good man
and times are too difficult.
But I'll never see her again. I swear.
I swear our on our love.
Swear on Marceau's head.
I swear on Marceau's head.
Madame.
What is it ?
Is Monsieur with you ?
Can't she look after it.
Yes.
Monsieur, there's a policeman for you,
Inspector Marchetti. He says it's urgent.
Tell him to wait.
What's he want from me ?
Inspecteur ?
Monsieur Schwartz.
Did you see this ?
Yes. I'm a subscriber.
You remember, when I arrived in June.
I was on the trail of a Communist cell.
Yes, vaguely. You know, during all that mess...
Yes. I established that they
printed their leaflets at your place...
Ah yes, yes.
So ?
Do you still have your printing machine ?
You know, during the exodus,
the sawmill was looted twice...
...they took everything...
...including the printing machine.
Funny booty for a looter, right ?
Germans Out!
Why would I have anything to do with that ?
I don't want to lose
the only customers I have left.
Tell me, the brother of the Mayor, Marcel Larcher...
Yes. Well ?
Do you think he's still a Communist ?
I know nothing about it. Do you think
if he was a Communist, he'd tell me ?
Monsieur Schwartz, you already lied to me
four days ago about your employee, Sarah.
I passed on that because it was a trifle,
but today the case is much more serious.
Let me ask you a clear and precise question.
Do you know if Marcel Larcher's activities
have been a little different lately ?
Something out of the ordinary.
No. I've not seen anything.
You know, Mr. Larcher is a work-horse.
He says nothing, he does his work.
I've seen nothing.
Please.
Very well. Thank you.
The noose is tightening, Marcel.
I don't know what you're talking about.
Stop taking me for an mug.
The police just left my house.
They're coming back here.
So obviously they suspect you.
I covered for you this morning.
But if you used string from here
for the bundles of papers...
... they'll realize it's
not at all the same string.
You're really irresponsible.
Thanks for warning me.
I finished typing the Directive on Hunting.
How are you ?
Marchetti is putting me on the spot following a...
Ah well, perhaps it's not too bad.
You'd have preferred to investigate it ?
Yes.
Oh good ! Come on.
If it was me in charge of the investigation,
there'd be no risk of finding culprit.
But Marchetti will find them.
I didn't understand that.
I'm a fool. I should never have made my
disapproval of Montoire and Collaboration plain.
It's not you who's a fool.
You're a sincere man.
Well nowadays that's the same thing.
I'm not going to be able to do
anything for this crackpot !
I think you're very hard on them
They're amateurs, they've no chance.
Monsieur Larcher ?
Come Gustave.
Monsieur Larcher ! You can't come into a class.
Have you spoken to Mr Bériot ?
Gustave, please.
Hurry up.
Don't move.
I can't let you take him like this.
It's contrary to all regulations.
Screw the rules.
Mr Bériot ?
Mr Bériot !
Mr Bériot.
What is it Papa ?
Where's your bike ?
Papa, what is it ?
I have to go on a trip, Gustave. For a long time.
We're leaving ?
No. Not we. Me.
But what about me ? Where am I going ?
To Uncle Daniel's.
I don't want to go
and live with Uncle Daniel.
I'm not asking for your opinion, Gustave.
Listen. I have something important
to tell you. And there's not much time.
The lady this morning. You don't know her.
Nobody came this morning, you hear me ?
But you'll come to see me at Uncle Daniel's ?
Don't tell me you're involved in this !
I didn't tell you.
Can you look after the kid, yes or no ?
You know very well it's yes.
Otherwise you wouldn't have brought him.
Marcel, do you realize that I'll
have to report your visit to the police ?
Do what you want.
That's really you, that is !
I just ask you to do what you have to
and you give me a morality lesson !
It's always been like that.
What are you going to do now ?
It's hard to answer you.
Why ?
You'll have to tell the police.
You are intolerable.
I'd like to point out that the officer
in charge of this case, lives here.
You're lucky he wasn't here.
It's not luck. I know he's currently
snooping around the sawmill.
So if you have to report, then report me.
Just give me 2 or 3 hours.
Here. This is a letter for the little one...
...if something goes wrong.
You're going to stay a little while with Uncle.
Remember what I told you ?
I'll show you where you're going to sleep.
Come.       Come on.
The bag ?
It's nice to have spared us a long search.
Thank you.
You continue to deny you know this man ?
It's not my fault if he says he knows me.
We have a very reliable witness who
saw you together a few days ago.
Well, he's wrong.
Tell me, Madame Richard.
Who's going to feed your children tonight ?
Because you're keeping me here ?
Bring in Larcher, please.
Here are the pieces of string which tied up
the bundles of newspapers, Madame Richard.
It appears they come from the
sawmill where Monsieur Larcher works.
Can you explain that too ?
She can't tell you anything.
She's not aware of anything.
I'm sorry, love.
I made this woman my mistress so
I could do this action with the Post.
I used our meetings to advance my plan.
And this morning afterwards...
I used the opportunity of her being
asleep in the van, to insert the flyers.
I re-tied the bundles with the sawmill twine.
I didn't think anyone would see the difference.
Well, that's it.
That explains why the
witness saw them together.
We were thinking of politics
and it was adultery.
How long have you been meeting ?
A few weeks.
Listen, do with me what you want,
but don't dirty her reputation.
A POW's wife, adultery, this is serious.
That could upset the Judge on the case, Monsieur.
Forgive me Suzanne.
Where did you go for your little meetings ?
Near the cemetery.
In the mornings.
Well, that's nice.
Good. We'll remand both of you...
...and the judge will do whatever he wishes.
Eat your soup while it's hot, Gustave.
Thank you, Maria.
Thank you.
Your brother will be transferred to...
Not in front of the little one.
Is your soup good, Gustave ?
Yes.
When will Papa come back ?
We don't know yet, darling.
You never called me darling before.
I'm really sorry for this situation, but the
charges against your brother are overwhelming.
He confessed, anyway.
Do you know what he risks ?
Well first, administrative detention...
.. under the law of 1939, and then...
After that, I don't know.
Six months or a year.
And the Postmistress ?
The judge swallowed the story of adultery.
He told me he was going to give her
a little lecture, but not prosecute her.
You want more soup, darling ?
But, I haven't finished.
Ah yes. You're right.
So if you want me to move out...
No.
Not at all.